Guide to the Ithiel Town papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ithiel Town papers
1801-1855
MS 499
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(1 box, 1 folio)
Correspondence from John Allan, William Hayward and Theodore Strong, a notebook of mathematical exercises, photostatic copies of letters of patent for improvements on bridges and one architectural drawing of Jones Court, built in New York City for James I. Jones. Also included is a scrapbook assembled by Town's daughter, Etha Town Peters.
Town, Ithiel, 1784-1844
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were the gifts of William T. Peters, son-in-law of Ithiel Town, 1858, and of the Collector's Shop, New Haven, Connecticut, 1939. The negatives for the photostatic copies were loaned by C. W. Whittlesey in 1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ithiel Town (1784-1844), architect; first major work was Center Church in New Haven, Connecticut.; subsequently designed many buildings in New Haven, Hartford, New York City, Indianapolis, Raleigh, North Carolina.; worked in partnerships based in New York, 1827-; in 1820 was granted a patent for a truss bridge and became known as the foremost bridge-builder in the United States.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence from John Allan, William Hayward and Theodore Strong, a notebook of mathematical exercises, photostatic copies of letters of patent for improvements on bridges and one architectural drawing of Jones Court, built in New York City for James I. Jones. Also included is a scrapbook assembled by Town's daughter, Etha Town Peters.
Mathematics; Albums (Books); Architects; Allan, John, 1777-1863; Hayward, William; Peters, Etha L. Town, 1809-1871; Strong, Theodore, 1779-1855; Town, Ithiel, 1784-1844
- Original accession
  - Correspondence
    - John Allan:
      - 2 ALS to Ithiel Town, 1834, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - ALS to William T. Peters, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - William Hayward: ALS to Ithiel Town, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Theodore Strong: 2 ALS to Ithiel Town, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mathematical exercises, 1801-? (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of patent for improvements on bridges (photostatic copies), 1820, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Architectural drawing of Jones Court, Circa 1826-1828 (Box 2)
  - Etha L. (Town) Peters: scrapbook of drawings and engravings, 1838 January (Box 1, Folder 5)